<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>No penalty, no peace in a sermon preached at the assizes held at Leicester, August the 10th, 1682 / by Thomas Ashenden ...</title>
            <author>Ashenden, Thomas, 1648 or 9-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B17254</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12786529</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205165</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240953207</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3973</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12786529</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B17254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205165)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1518:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>No penalty, no peace in a sermon preached at the assizes held at Leicester, August the 10th, 1682 / by Thomas Ashenden ...</title>
                  <author>Ashenden, Thomas, 1648 or 9-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Political science.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">State, The.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205165:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205165:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>No Penalty, No Peace,</hi> IN A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES held at LEICESTER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>August</hi> the 10th, 1682.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Ashenden,</hi> Rector of <hi>Dingley</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Smith</hi> in <hi>Russel-street, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent-Garden,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:205165:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205165:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable <hi>Richard Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts,</hi> Esq; high Sheriff of the County of <hi>Leicester,</hi> and to the Worshipful the Gentlemen of the Grand Jury.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Favourable Reception this Discourse gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally had at its delivery, and the particular Approbation you all did me, the extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry honour to express of it, might perhaps be Arguments to men of a temper different from mine, to affect the gratifying themselves farther in the publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But I have so great and just a Consciousness of my own weakness and inability, that truly I had not the least imagination of so doing, had not you all Gentlemen in an especial way (uncapable of any denial) laid your commands upon me.</p>
            <p>That it appears therefore at all is in obedience to you, that it comes abroad so soon, was one part and pressure of your Injunctions. And yet it will be impossible for me to acquit this hastiness of Printing, from unpardonable Levity and Vanity, unless you interpose your Favour and Authority betwixt me and Censure.</p>
            <p>For pray let me presume to say, that the following Discourse, now is no longer mine, the Case is wholly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, so that what was lately my Sermon is now entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become your Book.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205165:3"/>
            <p>These considerations have forced me upon the great hazard of exposing these weak lines to the deliberate and dangerous tast of Ocular Perusal, where such faults will be sure to be stopt and arraigned, as made a shift (in the late hast and hurry) to escape the notice and censure of your Ears.</p>
            <p>However, Here it is <hi>verbatim,</hi> the same as at its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery; nor have I dared to add or diminish (though even my weak sight discovers many loose lines and abrupt Periods) least I should belye the Title Page.</p>
            <p>I shall (I fear) have great need of your Patronage and Protection, to temper and alleviate such Cavils and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies as will be thrown by some unreasonable men of these unbridled headstrong times. Who, if toucht (tho' never so gently) sharpen their (reverberating) tongues like a Serpent, and have Adders poyson under their lips, <hi>Psal. 140.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude with my most humble thanks for your many honourable Favours to me, and with my hearty Prayers to God to encrease and prosper in you that Piety, Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Courage, which you so zealously express; (as far as in you lies) to advance the Peace and Prosperity of this Church and State. <hi>I am</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your most Obliged, Humble Servant. <hi>T. A.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205165:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JUDGES the XVII. vers. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>In those days there was no King in <hi>Israel,</hi> but every man did that which was right in his own Eyes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AFTER the lamentable, yet not (altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) inglorious fall of <hi>Sampson</hi> (in the end of the preceeding Chapter) who sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed Three Thousand Philistins to his last rage and revenge, and raised a Monument to his victorious Death out of the ruins of the very Temple of <hi>Dagon</hi> their Idol God; after this famous Prince (who judged <hi>Israel</hi> twenty years) we read of no Judge or Governour in the Land till old <hi>Eli,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.18. though we meet with some occurrences of note, and very remarkable Transactions in this <hi>Interregnum</hi> (as I may call it) or pause of State Government: but yet such as too plainly express the disordered constitution of those times, and strange irregularities of Impiety and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205165:4"/> as if all Religion and good Order did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vanish upon the cessation of the civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, of which misdemeanours the Chapter of my Text begins with one, and that of no trivial concern, you have the Narrative of it in the five verses before my Text; And 'tis how that <hi>Micah</hi> and his Idolatrous Mother contrived the making of a graven Image, and a molten Image, and they were kept in <hi>Micha</hi>'s House, vers. 4. and to denote the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited extravagance of this superstitious humour, 'tis said in the verse afore my Text, and the man <hi>Micah</hi> had an house of gods, and made an Ephod and Teraphim, and Consecrated one of his Sons who became his Priest: But here the words of my Text forthwith interpose, and by way of serious reflection on such disorderly proceedings, and to suggest plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us the cause and occasion of the foregoing Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, it tells us that in those loose and irregular times, <hi>there was no King in</hi> Israel, no supreme Power to restrain such Enormities, and therefore no better could be expected, then that <hi>every man should do what was right in his own Eyes;</hi> when there was no legal restraint to the contrary, no civil Power to oblige men to a strict observance of the standing Rule and Form of the Mosaick Law. But least I should seem to take too large and unwarrantable a Liberty with the words of my Text, and to force more from it in conclusion than it will fairly bear, (for the sum of my present Discourse will be to prove that where there is no exercise or exertion of civil Power in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties for offences, there is little or no likelihood of Peace either in Church or State) least my Text, I say,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205165:4"/> should seem to weak a foundation for this super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structure; since it seems to point at the matter of false Rellgion only, or mistakes in Divine Worship; I will by your leave draw in one or two neighbouring paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel Texts to its assistance, and to my own in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it. You have heard already what happened in <hi>Micha</hi>'s case, how great and gross Idolatry he and his Mother were guilty of; the occasion of which my Text doth palpably assign to the intermission of State-Government in those days, or because <hi>there was no King in</hi> Israel. Every man for want of a coercive Guide in the right and rational Worship of the Deity, was misled by his own private fancy and fond hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour into false Worship and Irreligion, which yet seemed <hi>right to him in his own Eyes,</hi> though in its self most abominably Idolatrous. This happened in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Ecclesiastical for want of a restraining Power, or a strict coercive Guide and Governour in things Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; <hi>In those days there was no King in</hi> Israel, and consequently every man drew his Religion by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del and platform of his particular opinion. But the mischievous consequence of the want of a King or supreme Governour ended not here, for it hath been not seldom observed that the ruin of a Nation begins with a corruption or neglect of Divine Worship, and therefore as this People the Jews were misled by their own private fancies in matters of Worship for defect of a Governour; so for the same reason they lasht out into all extremities of Pride and Cruelty, Violence and Rapine, Lust and Injustice, in matters Political, or in their behaviour and carriage one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; having no King to keep them within the bounds
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205165:5"/> of the first Table, and to oblige them to a right and strict Worship of God, they forthwith stuck at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but without remorse or regard broke through all the prohibitions of the second. The Chapter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly following that of my Text, begins with these very words, <hi>in those days there was no King in</hi> Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: Prefacing (as it were) the Violence and Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice the Danites there offered to this same <hi>Micah</hi> in Plundering his House, with this cause and occasion thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> this was done because <hi>there was no King in</hi> Israel, to restrain and punish such Enormities. Again, the nineteenth Chapter begins with the same words, and it came to pass in those days when <hi>there was no King in</hi> Israel, and soforth, where you may read a dismal relation of a horrid Rape and Murther committed at once upon the Body of a Levites Concubine; the reason of all these and the like flagitious outrages is affixt (as I told you) by the first verse of the nineteenth Chapter, to the being of <hi>no King in</hi> Israel.</p>
            <p>This short <hi>Prooemium,</hi> as it doth in little display to your quick sagacity a prospect of my ensuing Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, so I hope it hath removed some rubs in my way, whereby my progress might have been less plain and intelligible.</p>
            <p>My Text then doth easily seem to me to furnish us with these Four Propositions; First, That in matters of Religion and Worship, many things may seem right to men in their own Eyes, which in their own Nature are quite otherwise.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:205165:5"/>
            <p>Secondly, That Errors and Abuses of this kind fall under the Cognizance and Correction of the Civil Magistrate.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That 'tis no just Plea of Exemption from Punishment, for men to alledg, that they follow their Conscience, or (as my Text hath it) <hi>do what is right in their own Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, That in matters Political, without Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Restraints and Punishments for breaches of the Second Table, all Civil Societies wou'd be destroyed, and all things run into Desolation and Confusion.</p>
            <p>First, I say that in matters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis a strange and surprizing thing seriously to consider that Truth which is the natural and adequate Object of our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, shou'd have so few Adherents, especially when we consider that it shines by no mutuatitious Light, that it utterly disowns all false <hi>fucus</hi> and puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling disguises, presenting it self (unless it be our fault) always in its own simple beauty plain and naked to the Intellect; and on the contrary, that its Mimick Error, which dare never appear bare-fac'd, nor by its own name, but is forced to steal false Vizors, Disgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and Mock-truths, to insinuate and recommend it self, 'tis strange, I say, that Error and Mistake, which is always forced to borrow some faint Aires and gloomy Shades from Truth, shou'd pass for the real Substance, whereas the true and native Beauty of Verity affects us very coldly, and is too often glanced over unregard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. We become easily enamour'd of Cheat and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205165:6"/> but are dull and insensible of the Beauty of Holiness, as the Scripture Phrases it. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.21. 'Tis so, and as <hi>Laban</hi> the subtle <hi>Syrian</hi> jugled the blear-eyd <hi>Leah</hi> into <hi>Jacobs</hi> Bed, instead of the Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and well favour'd <hi>Rachel;</hi> so the Devil doth ingage the greatest part of men in the Embraces of Error, of all whom, I fear very few are undeceiv'd by the dawning Light, and like <hi>Jacob</hi> find their mistake in the Morning, they diein Delusion.</p>
            <p>Religion, or the right knowledg and adoration of the Almighty sprang up with Man in the very Morning of his Creation, and the Laws of both Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles (whose Original, 'tis true, was kept in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chives of Eternity) were Engraven in the heart of Man, and Woven into the very Principles of his Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence in more lively and durable Characters than those Engraven by the finger of God in the Tables of stone; in a word, the Notions of Piety and Justice, as they were plain, so were they indeleble: And this Satan the Enemy of Mankind quickly observ'd, he knew too, and concluded, that if no stop were interpos'd, no Amusement, Diversion or Delusion, presented to draw Mankind out of this plain and right Road of true Religion, it wou'd by necessary consequence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duet them to Happiness. To Eradicate the Notion of a Deity he thought was impracticable, he was resolved therefore to blur, deface and confuse Mens Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Godhead, and in effect, by this means he concluded more mischief might be done, than by fruitless Attempts of absolute Atheism. Accordingly by little and little he drills Men off from a Spiritual and Reasonable Service of the invisible God; by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205165:6"/> he materializes their Conception of him, as well as sensualizes their Inclinations and Affections; so that instead of one true God, he Enslaves them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and to the whole Creation; no Object so Vile and Contemptible, no Worship so Cruel, Servile and Ridiculous, but they bow and stoop to it, after the Devil had once stampt it with the false mark of a God and Religion, <hi>Oppida tota Canem venerantur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Juven. Sat.</hi> 15. Thus they turned the Glory of God into the similitude of on Ox that eateth Hay, saith the Royal <hi>Psalmist.</hi> When they had once left the right way they wandred in a Thousand Errors and Mazes of false Worship, when they had forsaken the reasonable Service of the true God, they were En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in Abominations without number; they Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship'd their own handy-work, Stocks and Stones, they Ador'd the Host of Heaven, and the Gods of every Nation; and those self same Persons that grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at God's easie and equal Service, and thought it much to walk mournfully before the Lord of Hosts, <hi>Malach.</hi> 3.14. these very Men and Women cou'd yet without grief or regret Sacrifice their Sons and their Daughters by Fire unto Devils, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.6. &amp; 2 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.17, 18. And this horrid piece of unnatural hellish Religion cou'd seem right in those Eyes, that cou'd not drop a Tear at the dreadful sight and loud cries of their burning Babes.</p>
            <p>Thus in the days of old, Religion was aped and falsified in a Thousand ridiculous shapes and misrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentations, and was drawn by the Devils own hand with such particular glances and allurements as the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205165:7"/> of the times, the tendences of Mens debauch'd Fancies, and his own designs required; innumerable diversities and mock shapes of Worship deluded poor Mortals, the true Religion all the while being opprest and cover'd under the nasty Rubbish of Idolatry and Superstition.</p>
            <p>But to draw my reflections into a narrower com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass, and to be more particular and pertinent to my purpose; the Devil did not only heretofore confound the genuine Worship of the Deity, with several mock shews and vain pageantry of Religion: but he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to play the same game still after the appearance of Christianity, by broaching Heresies and Scisms of all sorts, and by sowing Tares amongst the Wheat; which he hath done with such fatal success, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now Seventeen Hundred Years (very near) since Christianity was promulgated, and not much less since the true model and platform of it (the New Testament I mean) was delivered to us, to be for ever the Archetipe Rule and Standard of Faith and Practice; yet, from this plain and uniform model de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed for the help and rule of our Edification, have in all Ages been drawn by the warm Fancies of busie Enthusiasts, and the like, such monstrous Medlies, and odd Landskips of Opinions, as (in another kind) the most extravagant conceits of Poets and Painters have never equal'd; and truly I think one and the other have some grounds much alike for their Whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, I am sure they have each of them had too much of one Priviledge, and that is the <hi>Quidlibet Audendi Potestas.</hi> Hor. <hi>de Art. Poet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:205165:7"/>
            <p>But to come nearer home still, what makes so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poor deluded Souls in these distracted Kingdoms despise the Establish'd Religion, stampt with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Divine and Humane Laws, and instead of it grow so zealously fond of Seditious Noise and Soothing Nonsence? How patiently can Men Week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trudge (far above a Sabbath Days Journey) to hear the voice of a stranger,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.</note> so called by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior.</p>
            <p>Why shou'd they so readily and freely give their Money for that which is not Bread,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 5 1, 2.</note> as the Prophet complains,</p>
            <p>When they have Wine and Milk at home; when the Word is Preached agreeable to Christs Gospel at their own Door, purely and sincerely, constantly and carefully, zealously and devoutly? Why shou'd so many of our Country-men be impos'd upon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the pious usage of our Fore-fathers, their own Duty, and the known Laws of the Land, to leave the Assembling themselves together, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake the Communion of Saints, and follow after Novelty and New-fangledness?</p>
            <p>What forcible Cause is it that perswades them to go through Deserts where there lies no way, but the way of the Lord have they not known,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wisd.</hi> 7.</note> as the Wise Man saith.</p>
            <p>What makes the rough and rugged, the cross and crooked way of Schism and Sedition seem right to 'em in their own Eyes, leaving the pleasant ways and peaceable paths of Truth and Wisdome, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> calls 'em?</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:205165:8"/>
            <p>Why shou'd Quirks and Cavils, Difficulties and Obscurities, Niceties and Novelties, Faction and Fancy, prevail more with them, than the Reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Plainness of the Established Religion, than the Security and Perspicuity of <hi>the good old way?</hi> what cou'd send 'em such strong Delusion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.</note> that they shou'd so stedfastly believe a Lie.</p>
            <p>To speak here of the distant and more remote Causes of our Divisions, to shew the first springs and wheels of our Dissention, how they are ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer'd out by dark and deep Engeneers invisibly, and made to work slily and insensibly upon such as are to be Implements and Properties upon occasion, and to do the work of Ambitious and Factious Statists; to declare to you the several subtle Agents and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missaries that cooperate in this business, to tell you the Methods and Machinations, the Tricks and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues, the Devices and Designs, the Intent and End of their Mission; to shew you how that these Artists can make any thing appear as they gloss it, so that what they please shall seem right in the Eyes of the deluded, in a word, how they induce the Credulous to use Christian Liberty for a Cloak of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiousness,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16.</note> as saith the Apostle.</p>
            <p>To declare, I say, all this, belongs rather to a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Tract, than a Discourse of this Place and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>I will now rather content my self with the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and more apparent Causes of our present Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, and I shall truble you no farther, than with the bare naming of such Inveaglements as make the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205165:8"/> several Modes of Religion and false Worship in these our Days, seem right in the Eys of the Superstitious and Seditious.</p>
            <p>The First general Cause I take to be, Ignorance and Simplicity on the one side, and Hypocrisie and and Subtlety on the other, I mean the Insinuations of the pretended Teachers, which were long since described by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the Third Chapter of his Second Epistle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> the Fourth, Fifth, Sixth and Seventh Verses, where he tells us, That they are Traytors and Heady, that they have a form of Godliness, but deny the Power thereof, that they creep into Houses, and lead Captive silly Women, ever learning, and never able to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Truth. In which words (if we Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the behavior of our Modern Canting Holder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forths) we have their picture and posture so exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly described, that unless the Apostle shou'd have named them all severally by their names, they cou'd not have been pointed at more directly.</p>
            <p>A Second Cause may be, Easiness and Credulity, which is accordingly work'd upon by these sly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors that Trade in our Conventicles: They know very well that the Affections and Passions of silly Men and Women (as they are more easily stirred, so they) touch more sensibly, and operate in their motion more violently than rational Conviction and calm Perswasion; and herein lies the great Cheat of Canting Whining Applications; they produce very sensible and passionate Emotions in a seft and easie Auditory; and this forsooth, and this alone must be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205165:9"/> the operation of Gods Word and Spirit, this is Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, this is the Power of God unto Salvation; when as alas, all this pathetick Noise and moving Gestures of the cunning Speaker, never passed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the lower Region of the Passions, never reach'd the Seat of the Reason and Understanding of such as hear them.</p>
            <p>A Third Cause of these pleasing and plausible mistakes in matters of Religious Worship, is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable wresting and distorting of Scripture, such places more especially, as being simply taken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out relation to the Occasion or Context, seem plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to speak the sence of these People. Now these places out of Gods Word being dextrously timed and apply'd by cunning Crafts-men to Factious and Superstitious Fancies, already tainted and infected, rivet the Delusion irreversibly in the crafie opinion of the Brainsick-Party, of this St. <hi>Peter</hi> complains in the Third Chapter of his Second Epistle, Verse Sixteen, telling us that Men unlearned and unstable do wrest the Scriptures to their own Destruction.</p>
            <p>A Fourth, And a very Powerful Cause to make any sort of Religious Worship seem right in Mens own Eyes, is Prejudice; which hath several Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Divisions, yet it may be described in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to be, a fond and foolish Resolution to be one way alone in the right, right or wrong.</p>
            <p>There is a Prejudice of Birth and Education, which possesses some so violently with the opinion of their Pore-fathers, that a Man wou'd think they received a tincture in their very Generation, and grew of their Parents Sect <hi>ex Traduce.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:205165:9"/>
            <p>To conclude this point, Religious Prejudice is sometimes Interest and Worldly Design, sometimes Custom, sometimes Passion, sometimes Vain-glory and Ambition to lead a Faction, and govern the Crowd; sometimes 'tis Shame and a dilingenious Reluctancy to acknowledg our mistakes, left by so doing we should give our Father, our Selves and the whole Party the Lie, sometimes 'tis meer Fancy and Humor, and not seldome 'tis Malice, wilful Perverse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Obstinacy that confirms us in false Worship and Superstition.</p>
            <p>Lastly, As great a Cause as any of the above mentioned, to Create Divisions and Factions in Church or State, is Toleration, Liberty and Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and indeed the Text takes notice of no other, as if this alone were of it self sufficient to occasion diversities of Worship, <hi>viz.</hi> The Cessation of Civil Power and Punishment; for when Men may do any thing that they think right, they will go near to think any thing right, and this brings me to my Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Observation, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That Errors and Misdemeanors in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, fall under the Cognizance and Correction of the Civil Magistrate; This is so plainly suggested in my Text, that it needs no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demonstration, for it was, because <hi>there was no King in</hi> Israel, that <hi>Micah</hi> ventured upon such gross Idolatry, and it was Liberty and Impunity that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it all right in his own Eyes, <hi>In those Days,</hi> &amp;c. That Kings and Princes had the care of both Tables <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> their char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is blam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Scripture,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205165:10"/> and that they are therefore Supreme Supervizors and Governors in matters pertaining to Religion, is Evident, and that they Ordered and Regulated in Ecclesiastick, as well as Secular Causes, appears in the History of <hi>Moses, Joshua, Solomon, Hezekiah, Josiah, &amp;c.</hi> Besides, we read every where, that Gods Word and Message concerning Religion and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship was always directed to Kings and Princes by his Messengers the Prophets; they were command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to out down the Groves, to break down the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and Altars of Idols, to take away abuses and corruptions in Religion, and the like, and they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly Govern'd the Priests, ordered their Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, removed the Ark from place to place, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Priests to read the Book of the Law, and to reduce things to a conformity with it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, Prophesying of the Church in the Evangelical times, That Kings and Queens are Fosterers and Nurses of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. &amp; 60.16.</note>And in the primitive and purest times of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, the Christian Emperours did not only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the general Councels of the Bishops, but the good Emperour <hi>Constantine</hi> (though a temporal Prince) thought it no sacrilegious encroachment, no sin of <hi>Ʋzziah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cro.</hi> 26.16.</note> to judge in Causes Ecclesiastical, as he did between the <hi>Donatians</hi> and <hi>Catholicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And farther, as if this spiritual supremacy were not only a Divine Right, but a natural positive pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of Kings,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Politic.</hi> lib. 3.</note>
               <hi>Aristotle</hi> tells us <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The King is Lord and Ruler
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205165:10"/> in things that appertain to the Gods. 'Tis true, that our profest Enemies of the Papal and Presbyterian Faction, are violent opposers of these assertions; their Pride and Ambition will allow of no Rival or Competitour, much less a supream Governour in Ecclesiastick affairs; they wholy engross the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of the Church, and exclude temporal Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from interposing there, that they may with greater ease inslave the State, and tyrannize over our Souls, Bodies, and Estates, with the old plausible cheat of <hi>in ordine ad spiritualia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But surely temporal Princes are grown wise enough (by this time of day) to discover the old Imposture, and to assert their Royal Prerogative in this point, against the subtle, and equally dangerous encroachments both of Pope and Presbyter. For not a few Princes have found to their cost by fatal experience; that spiritual and secular supremacy are inseparable, like twins they are born and bred toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and have always been found to sympathize so far, that the one being extinct, the other doth not long survive. Let Princes be but once baffled out of their Ecclesiastical Superiority, and 'twill not be long e're they will be trampled upon from <hi>Rome</hi> (as once Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> served the Emperour) with the prophane insulting insolence of <hi>super aspidem cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabis &amp; basiliscum;</hi> which our Phanatick Reformers in the late Tragick times thus Englished, To bind their Kings in Chains, and their Nobles in Fetters of Iron, such honour have all his Saints.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:205165:11"/>
            <p>But to proceed the reformation of abuses in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, hath been proved from Scripture, and the usage and consent of the primitive Church to belong to the civil Power, though much more might be said: And 'tis not only the respective Duty of Kings, if they regard the Glory of God (whose Ministers they are) but 'tis also their nearest interest and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial concern, if they value the honour and safety of their own regality, to prevent the rise and growth of divisions and discentions in Religion, and to oppose and crush the propagation of false Doctrine, Heresie, and Scism, which (sooner or later) never fail to hatch and engender Sedition, privy Conspiracy and Rebellion: Too late, and too clear Proofs evince the truth of this.</p>
            <p>Alas, 'tis neither the Priest nor the Prophet can stop the broaching and running on of Scism and Faction, nor hinder the fatal mischiefs that flow from separations in Religious Worship, without the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of penal Laws, without the effectual inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of the temporal Sword: If Disputing, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; or Preaching, could have effected any thing, 'tis most probable that all our late distractions and present divisions, had been cured and convinced, as well as baffled and confuted, <hi>si pergama dextra,</hi> &amp;c. No, no, the perverse heretical Spirit that agitated in the first ages of Christianity, worketh yet still in the Children of disobedience: And when good and learned men offer at a Cure by publick Writing and Dispute, the fruitless consequence shews plainly that the wrong remedy is applied, the malady lying more
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:205165:11"/> in the Perversness of the will than the mistake of the Intellect: And for this cause demonstration it self often fails of conviction, and the strongest and plainest truths urged home to Scismaticks, stay not: but are sent back in a faint retort, stuft more with weak evasions, and pevish cavil than right or reason▪ Whence 'tis apparent that Hypocrisy and Subtilty, Arrogancy and Obstinacy, not Reason or Judgment hold the Cudgels; 'Tis in vain therefore to hope that the strongest and most zealous Arguments will ever reduce Scism and Faction to an amicable compliance, since their pride always forearms them with a reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to demur at demonstration, and cavil at con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction. 'Tis the <hi>Argumentum bacillinum</hi> must do the work, no demonstration so convincing as that of a Penal Statute, no perswasion so pressing as that of a legal mulct. At least the example and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the Power and Presence of the temporal Prince, is necessary (next to Gods Grace) to the maintenance of true Religion and regular Worship. Nay the very presence alone of the Supream Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, and the awe of his personal appearance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the people, is of it self very often the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, encouragement, and life of Religion: <hi>A King sitting in the Throne of Judgment, scattereth away all evil with his Eyes,</hi> Prov. 20.8.</p>
            <p>When people are not engaged and pois'd by the reverential awe and dread of their Superiors Person and Power, but are Idle, Loose, and at Liberty; it hath been observed that the first degree of Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Faction hath been a Tinkering with their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205165:12"/> own Fancies about points of Religion, hammering out strange gods, and fondly forging new modes of Worship. We have a notable proof and instance of this in the 32 Chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> where the chiefest occasion of that abominable Idolatry of the molten Calf, was the Peoples impatience of <hi>Moses</hi> delay and stay in the Mount, his only abscence set their superstitious inclinations in a new ferment; and as if even Religion it self were flown away and departed in the Person of <hi>Moses,</hi> they set upon <hi>Aaron</hi> with this tumultuous exclamation; come make us Gods, for as for this <hi>Moses</hi> we wot not what is become of him. This People however (by the way) shewed more modesty and obedience than our modern Sectaries; for in the absence of the Civil Magistrate, they appeal to the High Priest for a Religion, whereas our Factious Dissenters will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther follow the Religion of Prince nor Priest.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The third Proposition imply'd in my Text is, That 'tis no just plea of exemption from punishment, for men to alledge that they follow their Conscience or (as my Text hath it) <hi>do what is right in their own Eyes.</hi> For if the Profession and Practice of the Christian Religion, as 'tis now by Law Established, be no farther obligatory than as it hits and suits the private Conscience of each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular man; the consequence is clear, and matter of Fact hath too lately convinc't us that a Torrent and Inundation of Irreligion, Libertinism, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theism, will certainly follow. This hath been (as I said) too evident from Fact it self, (the highest
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:205165:12"/> conviction) in our late deplorable confusions; nor doth it want its notional and speculative demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion too; for if private Conscience (so called) be in some men mere humour and whimsie, in many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, Mallice and Passion, in most men ignorance, Custom and Prejudice; what a monstrous medley of mischiefs must private Conscience necessarily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, when she is impregnate with such a lewd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, such a pernitious viperous brood? Besides, This destructive Principle sets up a Tribunal in every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate mans factious fancy (for though I have a sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred regard to the thing Conscience, yet I can allow it no better a name in the sense we now mention) and makes the Authority of Heav'n and Earth, and the Wisdom and Laws of a whole Nation to be of no effect, force or value, till they are sign'd and seal'd by the humoursom approbation of every sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious crazy Enthusiast, it inverts the whole Course of Nature, and the reason of things; it lays the Law at the Feet and Mercy of the offendour, and exalts the Felon to the Seat of the Judge: For there can be no whimsies so rediculous, no conceptions so monstrous, no tenets so blasphemous, no practices so mischievous, but will take sanctuary here, and plead a little to Impunity under pretence of this Liberty of Conscience, which cannot in short be better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed than as the Poet expresses <hi>Poliphemus,</hi> 'tis <hi>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum horrendum, informe, ingens, cui lumen ademptum,</hi> I am sure it hath proved as blind and bloody.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:205165:13"/>
            <p>For to mince the matter no longer, but to speak the naked truth, all this doleful noyse of scruple and tenderness, all the queremonious clamour is of a Nature quite contrary to what it appears, and the Arguings and Disputings of our Sectaries (in plain terms) is not for Truth but for Dominion; like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert and cunning Commanders, they amuse and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert us with dilatory, Treat, and Capitulation, till they can handsomly make head, and once again draw their Forces into the Field of Battle. Their voice is <hi>Jacobs</hi> voice, but their hands are the hands of <hi>Esau.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Undoubtedly we may thank our selves for the edge and keenness of our present divisions, and our manifold menacing mischiefs we may chiefly date from the late Toleration; such allowances proceed from Royal mercy and tenderness, 'tis true, but the dangers that always ensue are innumerable and grow to a formidable stature by insensible degrees, till at length they suck themselves into a State and Habit, strong enough for Rebellion, even from the Breasts of Royal Indulgence.</p>
            <p>If the good and wholsom Acts of Uniformity had been applied without remisness, we should by this time have found mens purses more tender than their Consciences; at least 'twould have done so much good, that the old <hi>Pique</hi> had been buried with this Generation, and the next would have conform'd of Course; whereas I fear the late long Impunity hath fixt the contagion in the very Vitals of our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205165:13"/> dissenting Brethren, and their Children will be taint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>ex traduce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay farther, There is a more mischievous conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence still from such grants of Liberty in Religious Worship, and we suffer the same Judgment the Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites did, in permitting the Canaanites to dwell among them, <hi>viz.</hi> Many even of us have been inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to go a whoring after their Gods, and as the Angel told the People at <hi>Bochim; They are left to be Thorns in our sides,</hi> Judg. 2.3.</p>
            <p>And yet I would not willingly be mistaken in this part of my Discourse neither, as if I hinted at a tyrannical and cruel Inquisition; I declare that I urge no unnatural force or usurpation over the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and thoughts of men, nor would I fetter or shackle the understanding (which is undoubtedly in Nature as free as the Will) much less would I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a Rape upon a truly tender and modest Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; or like the cruel Romanists, force a blind obedience upon any man: For, (as a worthy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine saith) <q>Our Church is not against any mans seeing spiritual truths with his own Eyes, only we would not have the blind presume to teach others to see, we would not have men think they see when they do not, which is the most certain way for them never to see at all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Our Church by applying the soft and gentle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies of statutable Punishments, never intended to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205165:14"/> force gross blindness, or impose the tyranny of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit faith upon any man, but rather the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, she carefully and wisely considered that a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle smart might make the scales peel off from mens Eyes, and by some little bitterness she des gns no more harm to them, than <hi>Tobias</hi> did to his old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by throwing gall in his Eyes to make him see.</p>
            <p>It is (to conclude this point) extreamly admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and incomprehensible to me, that so many of our Countrey-men should out of an odd pevish hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and most unaccountable Caprice, forsake that sober decent way of Worship, which the established law presses, which their gracious king and governour himself strictly observes, together which the Loyal No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Magistracy, and Gentry, and the most reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and learned Clergy of this Land, that they should, I say, leave these good, these great, these wise Examples, contrary to the obedient humble temper of Christians, contrary to the Prudence and Interest of rational men, and contrary to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest good Nature of true English-men; and all this out of a blind and ignorant compliance to the insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating hypocritical perswasions of a few leading Prejudic'd Presbyters: For true scruple of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot be said to urge them to this nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; not one of five hundred understanding the intrinsick State of the debate, any more than they doe <hi>Arabick:</hi> but granting that they could plead Christian scruple, how far would even that fall short of Justification, Seing that the commands to Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205165:14"/> are so absolute, so plain, so positive, and the pretences for Separation (even at best) so obscure, so weak, so dubious.</p>
            <p>In a word, The Faith of our Nonconformists is as blind and implicite as that of the Papists; the design of their Doctrines as subtle, sensual and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, and Lastly, My last Observation is, That without Legal Severities, and Temporal Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments of Secular or Political Misdemeanors, all Societies wou'd run the unavoidable danger of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion and Dissolution. The horrid outrages, and most flagitious Villanies of Robbery and Plunder, of Rape and Murder, which the Two next Chapters after that of my Text tell the lamentable Story of, these Villanies I say are prefaced (as it were) <hi>in limine;</hi> at the first Entrance of their Narration, with half my Text, <hi>In those Days there was no King in</hi> Israel: which inlet to those dismal Stories hints plainly to us the occasion of the lewd loose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of those abominable Times.</p>
            <p>We all know, and freely grant, ('tis true) that Propositions about right and wrong, just and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just, are as little liable to dispute and contest, and less subject to doubt and difficulty, than Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Theorems and Conclusions; for though they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so are acknowledged to be Truths of Eternal date, though their Evidency is Evinced with much pomp and state of formal demonstration, yet without all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205165:15"/> doubt, Moral Truths do most justly challenge the Precedence, as more easily clear, and with less trouble, demonstrable; or rather, the truth and surety of them is of such a Nature as less needs a demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; besides our natural impressions of Justice, and its contrary, are less obnoxious to Errors and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stakes, and oversights, (than Geometrical Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) they command universal assent, and assault our radical Reason so forcibly, as that the bare men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning of these Moral Truths is of it self irresistible proof, and without farther delay or dispute they themselves are their own demonstration.</p>
            <p>In a word, All Sects of Philosophers in all Ages have joyn'd Issue here; however they have in all things else thwarted each other, and there hath been a general concurrence of all Mankind, as to the common notions of Vertue and Justice: Here the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Platonicks ceaseth, and freely owns, that there are some undoubted fixt truths in Morality: and in this case the rigid Stoicks break the bands of Fate and Necessity, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that here there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And, as to this affair, <hi>Aristotle</hi> (who will hardly allow any Man but himself in the right) doth willingly shake hands with <hi>Socrates</hi> and the Moralists: <hi>Adeo illud ratum certum{que} est quod honestum,</hi> as one saith.</p>
            <p>But for all this, notwithstanding our concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Justice and Vertue are confessedly true, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205165:15"/> universally so, yet they wou'd all prove in effect but naked Notions, fruitless Speculations, and vain Ideas, without the awful terror of the <hi>Fasces</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curis,</hi> without the enforcement of the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, without the interposal of the Temporal Sword. And most undoubtedly, without these, that radical rule of Justice it self, that highest and most fixt truth in Nature, <hi>Quod tibi fieri non vis alteri ne feceris;</hi> even this wou'd as rarely and difficultly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in real Fact and Experiment, as the Philosophers Stone, or the admired Phaenix. <hi>Video meliora pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo{que} deteriora sequor,</hi> wou'd I fear, be the highest pitch of practical Morality, without the mediation of legal Punishments of all sorts.</p>
            <p>Not that I here slily suggest, as if the Essence and Obligation of Justice and Vertue had no other Being, no stronger a foundation, no longer a date, than that of positive Laws, and humane constitutions, God forbid.</p>
            <p>But I mean (in a word) that such is the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral corruption of humane Nature, so pressing are the present allurements of Profit and Pleasure, of Pride and Ambition; so forcible are the suggestions of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, Malice and Revenge; so distant are the Fears and Threats of the other World, and so Egging and Incouraging are the thoughts of Impunity here, that were it not more for fear of Temporal Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace and Punishment, than for any future Terrors
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205165:16"/> of Ruin hereafter, the World would become a Den of Bears and Tygers; and without doubt, Man wou'd be (in the state I speak of) <hi>Non solum lupus sed daemon homini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, I am inclined to think, that most Men dread the Presence of a Temporal Judg, more than they do the Appearance of the Lord of Hosts; that a Day of Assizes here on Earth strikes a greater hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in many, than the thoughts of the most dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Day of Judgment, and that the fear and shame of a Branding-Iron had kept more Men Honest and Just, than the appehensions of Everlasting Burnings, From which, good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>I will conclude all in desiring your Prayers to God with me, That he would so rule the heart of his chosen Servant <hi>Charles</hi> our King and Governor, that he (knowing whose Minister he is) may above all things seek God's Honor and Glory, and that we and all his Subjects (duly considering whose Authority he hath) may faithfully serve, honor and humbly Obey him, according to his Blessed Word and Ordinance: And that our Almighty Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wou'd be pleased to bless and keep all the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates and Judges of this Land, giving them grace to Execute Justice, and to maintain Truth. The Grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:205165:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>